Carolyn Jane Anderson

650 North Pleasant Street University of Massachusetts Amherst, MA 01003

Email: carolynander@umass.edu Web: http://candersl.github.io

Research Focus

My research focuses on context-sensitive expressions: words whose meanings change depending on who is speaking to whom, and where. These aspects of language are some of the most challenging for artificial intelligence to grasp, because they are situational, grounded, and interactive. Exploring these questions can help us understand general cognitive behavior such as theory of mind (our beliefs about other people's mental states), and help artificial intelligence learn to use language in a dynamic, responsive way.

Education

Ph.D. in Linguistics. University of Massachusetts, Amherst Dissertation: Shifting the Perspectival Landscape Advisors: Brian Dillon and Rajesh Bhatt

February 2021

M.A. in Linguistics. University of Massachusetts, Amherst

May 2019

B.A. in Linguistics and minor in Computer Science. Swarthmore College High Honors in Linguistics and Natural Language Models

June 2014

Positions

Wellesley College, Computer Science Department Assistant professor

Starting Fall 2021

BBN Technologies, Analytics and Machine Intelligence (Cambridge, MA) Research Intern

June 2018-August 2019

- Multi-dialect recurrent neural network language models for ASR
- Masked neural language model prediction for acoustic model rescoring
 Neural machine translation for post-processing numerical terms in ASR
 Statistical analysis of keyword search performance

Fulbright Canada, University of Victoria and McGill University

Fulbright Research Fellow, supervised by Leslie Saxon and Jessica Coon

Topic: Technology in First Nations Language Revitalization

September 2014-May 2015

Cornell University, Computer Science Department (Ithaca, NY)

Research Intern, supervised by Nate Foster

Topic: NetKAT: a domain-specific language for networking

May 2013-August 2013

Funding

BBN Technologies Research Fellowship

Spring 2019 and Spring 2020

Selkirk Linguistics Outreach Fund Award

2016

University of Massachusetts Amherst Fellowship

2015-2016

Fulbright Canada Research Scholarship	2014-2015
Programming Languages Mentoring Workshop Scholarship	2013 and 2014
Marianne Durand Frey '57 Scholar	2011-2014
National Merit Scholar	2010

Publications

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. *Tomorrow* is not always a day away. *Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung* (SuB) 23, 2019. **Selected for oral presentation**.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. Guess who's coming (and who's going): bringing perspective to the Rational Speech Acts framework. *Proceedings of the Society for Computation in Linguistics* (SCiL), 2019.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. 2016. Negation in Colonial Valley Zapotec. *Transactions of the Philological Society* 114(3).
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane, Nate Foster, Arjun Guha, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin, Dexter Kozen, Cole Schlesinger, and David Walker. NetKAT: Semantic foundations for networks. *ACM SIGPLAN-SIGACT Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages* (POPL), 2014. **Selected for oral presentation.**

Conference Presentations

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Diagnosing the semantics of perspectival expressions. Poster to be presented at the Annual Meeting of the Linguistic Society of America (LSA), 2021.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Coming in, or going out? Measuring the effect of discourse factors on perspective prominence. Poster presented at Experiments in Linguistic Meaning (ELM), 2020.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Tessa Patapoutian. Can neural network language models understand spatial perspective? Poster presented at the Bridging AI and Cognitive Science (BAICS) workshop, at the International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2020.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. Taking other perspectives into account: an RSA model of perspectival reasoning. Talk given at Rational Approaches in Language Science (RAiLS), 2019.
- 5. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Explaining the progressive motion verb puzzle in Zapotec. Talk given at the Texas Linguistics Society, 2019.
- 6. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. *Tomorrow* isn't always a day away. Poster presented at the 31st annual CUNY Human Sentence Processing Conference, 2018.
- 7. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. The San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec andative and venitive. Talk presented at the Society for the Study of Indigenous Languages of the Americas (SSILA) annual meeting, 2018. **Honorable Mention, Best Student Paper Presentation**
- 8. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. The andative and venitive construction in San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec. Talk presented at Multi-Verb Constructions: Semantic, Syntactic and Typological Perspectives (MVC), 2017.
- 9. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. The morphosyntax of negation in Colonial Valley Zapotec. Talk presented at the Society for the Study of Indigenous Languages of the Americas (SSILA) annual meeting, 2015.

- 10. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. La morfosintaxis de la negation en el zapoteco del Valle colonial. Talk presented at Coloquio sobre Lenguas Otomangues y Vecinas (COLOV) IV: Mario Molina Cruz, 2014.
- 11. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Language ideology and human rights doctrine in Morocco. Talk presented at New Ways of Analyzing Variation (NWAV) 42, 2013.

Manuscripts

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2020. Shifting the Perspectival Landscape: Methods for Encoding, Identifying, and Selecting Perspectives. Dissertation, University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2019. Tomorrow isn't always a day away: Non-utterance time readings of *tomorrow*. Under revision.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. 2019. Taking other perspectives into account: modeling the use of perspectival expressions in discourse. Ms., University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2017. The andative and venitive construction in San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec. Ms., University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 5. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2014. I talk it and I feel it: Language attitudes of Moroccan university students. Honors thesis, Swarthmore College.

Invited Talks

- 1. Cornell Tech, Department of Computer Science. 'Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2020.
- 2. Boston University, Department of Linguistics. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2020.
- 3. Colgate University, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 4. Denison University, Department of Data Analytics. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 5. James Madison University, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 6. Mount Holyoke College, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 7. Occidental College, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 8. University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 9. Wellesley College, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.

Other Presentations

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Reasoning about perspectives. Abstract selected for presentation at the Science Speed Geeking event at the XPrag Summer School, 2019.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Use your words (better): two projects on making better use of text for ASR. Intern presentation, BBN Technologies, 2019.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Neural networks for ASR: focusing on the text. Intern presentation, BBN Technologies, 2018.

Teaching

1.	Instructor, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department First Year Seminar: Technology for Language Revitalization	Fall 2019
2.	Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department Language Processing and the Brain (Instructor: Brian Dillon)	Fall 2019
3.	Instructor, Mt. Holyoke College, Computer Science Department Programming Languages	Fall 2018
4.	Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department Introduction to Linguistic Theory (Instructor: Seth Cable)	Spring 2017
5.	Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department Cognitive Modeling (Instructor: Gaja Jarosz)	Fall 2017

Advising

Undergraduate Research Assistants

Tessa Patapoutian Project: experimental and computational modeling of perspectival motion verbs	2019-2020
Alicia LeClair Project: Perspectival motion verbs in Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec	Spring 2017

Awards

Computing Research Association Outstanding Undergraduate Researchers Award Finalist	2014
The Linguistics Prize in Applications of Theory, Swarthmore College	2014
Phi Beta Kappa Inductee	2014
Philip M. Hicks Prize for Best Critical Essay	2013

Research Assistantships

University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department	Spring 2017
Oniversity of Massachuseus Annierst, Linguistics Department	3011118 2017

Research Assistant

Primary investigator: Seth Cable

Topic: Semantics of Endangered Languages in North America

University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department

Research Assistant

Primary investigator: Gaja Jarosz Topic: Computational phonology

Haverford College, Ticha Digital Humanities Project (Haverford, PA)

June 2014-August 2014

Fall 2016

Research Intern

Advisor: Brook Lillehaugen

Topic: Web-based preservation and presentation of Colonial Valley Zapotec texts

Service

Organizer: Neural Networks in Linguistics Reading Group 2018-2020

Graduate Representative to Faculty Meetings 2016-2017

Skype A Scientist Volunteer Spring 2020

Skills

Natural Languages

- Bangla (novice)
- French (advanced)
- German (intermediate)
- Modern Standard Arabic (intermediate)
- Spanish (intermediate)
- Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec (fieldwork)

Domain Specific Languages

- Tensorflow (intermediate)
- WebPPL (intermediate)

Programming Languages

- C++ (novice)
- Coq (intermediate)
- Figaro (intermediate)
- Haskell (novice)
- Java (intermediate)
- JavaScript (intermediate)
- Python (advanced)
- R (advanced)
- Racket (advanced)